Shivansh Singh

+60 162650096 | +91 9454960857 | ShivanshSingh1008@gmail.com | LinkedIn

Profile

Data Engineer with 5+ years of experience building large-scale data pipelines, ETL processes, and data warehouse solutions. Utilized technologies like **Python**, **SQL**, **Spark**, **Hadoop**, **Hive**, **ODI** to design data pipelines and warehousing systems that power insights and business intelligence for Banks and Telecom companies.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, SQL, Scala

Big Data Technologies: Spark, PySpark, Spark SQL, YARN, Hadoop, Hive, Impala, HDFS Data Engineering Tools: ODI(Oracle Data Integrator), Data Modelling, ETL/ELT data Pipeline

Orchestration: Zena

Certification: GCP Certified - Professional Data Engineer

EXPERIENCE

Maybank

June 2024 - Present

Senior Data Engineer

Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

- Led a team of 3 Data Engineers in designing, developing, and optimizing data pipelines and ETL processes.
- Migrated legacy ETL processes from Oracle Data Integrator (ODI) to **PySpark**, improving maintainability and reducing processing time by 20%.
- Optimized overall process performance through **Spark performance tuning**, improving job run times by 20% and efficiently managing a **15 Terabyte (TB)** dataset containing approximately **12 billion** records.

Vodafone

June 2022 – May 2024

Data Engineer

Pune, India

- Developed ETL pipelines to ingest raw CSV data, apply transformations using **PySpark**, and store the output in optimized Parquet format for efficient querying and downstream processing.
- Performed data analysis and ran complex queries on large datasets in **BigQuery**, generating actionable insights for business intelligence.
- Conducted in-depth data analysis using **Hive**, **Impala**, and **Spark SQL**, providing SIT/UAT fixes and ensuring smooth operations in the production environment.
- Worked on data ingestion pipeline to ingest flat files in the **Data Lake**.

Tata Consultancy Services

July 2019 - June 2022

ETL Developer

Bangalore, India

- Implemented the ETL process using **Oracle Data Integrator (ODI)**, configuring repositories, creating ODI models, and designing projects with interfaces, packages, procedures, variables, and knowledge modules for data processing on **Hadoop** and **HDFS**.
- Streamlined and simplified a complex ODI-based pipeline by removing redundant steps, eliminating hard coded components, and optimizing performance for downstream **Hive** queries—resulting in a more efficient and maintainable process.
- Collaborated with stakeholders to define and document user requirements, subsequently designing and executing unit test cases and test scripts.

EDUCATION

Rajiv Gandhi Proudyogiki Vishwavidyalaya

Indore, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics and Communication

July 2015 - June 2019